[His Holiness Pope Francis Filmed in Vatican City
[تم تصوير اللقاء مع قداسة البابا فرانسيس في الفاتيكان
First shown at TED2017]
ويتم عرضه لأول مرة في TED2017]
Good evening – or, good morning, I am not sure what time it is there.
مساء الخير - أو صباح الخير، لا أدري كم الساعة لديكم الآن.
Regardless of the hour, I am thrilled to be participating in your conference.
بغض النظر عن الساعة، أشعر بالحماس للمشاركة معكم في هذا المؤتمر.
I very much like its title – "The Future You" –
يعجبني عنوانه كثيراً - "The Future You" -
because, while looking at tomorrow, it invites us to open a dialogue today,
لأنكم بينما تنظرون للغد، فهو يدعوكم لفتح حوارٍ اليوم،
to look at the future through a "you."
للنظر إلى المستقبل من خلالكم "أنتم".
"The Future You:"
"The Future You:"
the future is made of yous, it is made of encounters,
فالمستقبل يُصنع منكم، إنّه مصنوعٌ من (المواجهين)،
because life flows through our relations with others.
لأن حياتنا تجري من خلال علاقاتنا مع الآخرين.
Quite a few years of life
فقد عزّزت سنوات حياتي القليلة قناعتي
that each and everyone's existence is deeply tied to that of others:
أن وجود كلٍّ منا مرتبط بشدة بوجود الآخرين:
life is not time merely passing by, life is about interactions.
فالحياة ليست مجرد وقتٍ يمضي، وإنما هي تفاعلنا مع من حولنا.
As I meet, or lend an ear to those who are sick,
وبما أنني أقابل أو أستمع للأشخاص المرضى،
to the migrants who face terrible hardships
والمهاجرين الذين يواجهون صعوباتٍ فظيعة
in search of a brighter future,
في البحث عن مستقبلٍ مشرق،
to prison inmates who carry a hell of pain inside their hearts,
ونزلاء السجن الذين يحملون جحيماً من الألم داخل قلوبهم،
and to those, many of them young, who cannot find a job,
وأولئك، الذين في معظمهم صغار، ممن لا يستطيعون إيجاد عمل،
I often find myself wondering:
دوماً أجد نفسي أتساءل:
"Why them and not me?"
"لماذا هم ولست أنا؟"
I, myself, was born in a family of migrants;
أنا، شخصياً، ولدت في عائلة من المهاجرين؛
my father, my grandparents, like many other Italians,
أبي وجدّّي، كالعديد من الإيطاليين الآخرين،
left for Argentina
غادرا إلى الأرجنتين
and met the fate of those who are left with nothing.
وواجها مصير أولئك الذين تُركوا بلا أيّ شيء.
I could have very well ended up among today's "discarded" people.
كان من الممكن جداً أن ينتهي الأمر بي اليوم بين أولئك الأشخاص "المنبوذين".
And that's why I always ask myself, deep in my heart:
ولهذا أسأل نفسي، في أعماق قلبي:
"Why them and not me?"
"لماذا هم ولست أنا؟"
First and foremost, I would love it if this meeting could help to remind us
أولاً وقبل كل شيء، سأحبّ لو يساعدنا هذا الاجتماع على تذكّر
that we all need each other,
أننا جميعاً نحتاج بعضنا البعض،
none of us is an island,
ولا أحد منّا يوجد على جزيرة،
an autonomous and independent "I," separated from the other,
"أنا" منفصلة ومستقلة عن الآخر،
and we can only build the future by standing together, including everyone.
ونحن لا يمكننا بناء المستقبل إلا بالوقوف معاً، بما في ذلك الجميع.
We don’t think about it often, but everything is connected,
إننا لا نفكر بالأمر كثيراً، ولكن كل شيءٍ متصل،
and we need to restore our connections to a healthy state.
ونحن بحاجةٍ لإعادة اتصالاتنا إلى حالتها الصحيّة.
Even the harsh judgment I hold in my heart
حتى الحكم القاسي الذي أحمله في قلبي
against my brother or my sister,
ضد أخي أو أختي،
the open wound that was never cured, the offense that was never forgiven,
والجرح المفتوح الذي لم يشف أبداً، والإساءة التي لم تغفر أبداً،
the rancor that is only going to hurt me,
والضغينة التي ستؤلمني وحدي فقط،
are all instances of a fight that I carry within me,
جميعها أمثلة عن صراعٍ أحمله معي،
a flare deep in my heart that needs to be extinguished
ونارٍ في قلبي تحتاج لأن تُطفأ
before it goes up in flames, leaving only ashes behind.
قبل أن يرتفع لهيبها مخلّفاً وراءه رماداً فقط.
Many of us, nowadays,
يميل العديد منّا اليوم
seem to believe that a happy future is something impossible to achieve.
إلى الاعتقاد بأن المستقبل السعيد مستحيل التحقّق.
While such concerns must be taken very seriously,
وعلى الرغم من أن هذه المخاوف يجب أن تؤخذ على محمل الجد،
they are not invincible.
فإنه من الصعب التغلّب عليها.
They can be overcome when we don't lock our door to the outside world.
يمكننا هزمها فقط في حال لم نقفل أبوابنا بوجه العالم الخارجيّ.
Happiness can only be discovered
فالسعادة يمكن اكتشافها فقط
as a gift of harmony between the whole and each single component.
كهبةٍ ناتجة عن الانسجام بين الجميع.
Even science – and you know it better than I do –
حتى العلم - الذي تعرفونه أكثر منّي -
points to an understanding of reality
يشير إلى فهم الواقع على أنه
as a place where every element connects and interacts with everything else.
المكان الذي يتصل فيه كل عنصر مع كل شيءٍ حوله ويتفاعل معه.
And this brings me to my second message.
وهذا يوصلني إلى رسالتي الثانية.
How wonderful would it be
كم سيكون الأمر رائعاً
if the growth of scientific and technological innovation
لو أن نمو الابتكار العلمي والتقنيّ
would come along with more equality and social inclusion.
يحقق المزيد من المساواة والاندماج الاجتماعي.
How wonderful would it be, while we discover faraway planets,
كم سيكون رائعاً، أنه وبينما نكتشف كواكب بعيدة
to rediscover the needs of the brothers and sisters orbiting around us.
أن نعاود اكتشاف حاجات الإخوة والأخوات الذين هم من حولنا.
How wonderful would it be if solidarity,
كم سيكون رائعاً لو أن التضامن،
this beautiful and, at times, inconvenient word,
هذه الكلمة الجميلة، وفي نفس الوقت غير المريحة،
were not simply reduced to social work,
لم يقتصر على العمل الجماعي فحسب،
and became, instead, the default attitude
بل أصبح بدلاً من ذلك الموقف التلقائي
in political, economic and scientific choices,
للخيارات السياسية والاقتصادية والعلمية،
as well as in the relationships among individuals, peoples and countries.
وكذلك في العلاقات بين الأفراد والشعوب والبلدان.
Only by educating people to a true solidarity
فقط من خلال تعليم الناس التضامن الحقيقيّ
will we be able to overcome
سنكون قادرين على التغلّب
the "culture of waste,"
على "ثقافة الهدر"،
which doesn't concern only food and goods
والتي لا تتعلق فقط بالأطعمة والبضائع
but, first and foremost, the people
بل، أولاً وقبل كل شيء، بالأشخاص
who are cast aside by our techno-economic systems
أولئك المهمشين من قبل أنظمتنا التقنية والاقتصادية
which, without even realizing it,
والتي، من غير أن تدرك ذلك حتّى،
are now putting products at their core, instead of people.
تضع منتجات الناس في جوهر اهتمامها بدلاً من الناس.
Solidarity is a term that many wish to erase from the dictionary.
إن التضامن مصطلحٌ يتمنى الجميع محوه من القواميس.
Solidarity, however, is not an automatic mechanism.
غير أنّه ليس آلية تلقائية.
It cannot be programmed or controlled.
فلا يمكن برمجته ولا التحكم به.
It is a free response born from the heart of each and everyone.
فهو استجابة طبيعية من قبل كلّ منا وجميعنا.
Yes, a free response!
نعم، استجابة طبيعية!
When one realizes
عندما يدرك المرء
that life, even in the middle of so many contradictions, is a gift,
أن الحياة، حتى في وسط الكثير من التناقضات، هي هبة،
that love is the source and the meaning of life,
وأن الحبّ هو مصدر الحياة ومعناها،
how can they withhold their urge to do good to another fellow being?
كيف له أن يكبح رغبته في فعل الخير لغيره؟
In order to do good,
ولفعل الخير،
we need memory, we need courage and we need creativity.
نحتاج إلى ذاكرة، نحتاج إلى شجاعة، ونحتاج إلى إبداع،
And I know that TED gathers many creative minds.
وأعلم أن TED يجمع الكثير من العقول المبدعة.
Yes, love does require a creative, concrete
نعم، فالحب يتطلب سلوكاً مبدعاً
and ingenious attitude.
ومتماسكاً وذكياً.
Good intentions and conventional formulas,
فالنوايا الحسنة والصيغ التقليدية
so often used to appease our conscience, are not enough.
التي غالباً ما تستخدم لإرضاء ضميرنا غير كافية.
Let us help each other, all together, to remember
دعونا نساعد بعضنا البعض سويّةً
that the other is not a statistic or a number.
لنتذكّر أن الآخر ليس إحصائيةً أو رقمًا.
The other has a face.
أن للآخر وجه.
The "you" is always a real presence,
أن الـ"أنت" هي وجود حقيقيّ،
a person to take care of.
أنها شخصٌ علينا الاهتمام به.
There is a parable Jesus told to help us understand the difference
هنالك قصة للمسيح قُصّت علينا لنفهم الفرق
between those who'd rather not be bothered and those who take care of the other.
بين أولئك الذي لا يحبّون أن يتم إزعاجهم وأولئك الذين يعتنون بالآخر.
I am sure you have heard it before. It is the Parable of the Good Samaritan.
أنا متأكدٌ أنكم سمعتموها من قبل. إنها قصّة السامري الصالح.
When Jesus was asked: "Who is my neighbor?" -
عندما سُئل المسيح: "من هو جاري؟"
namely, "Who should I take care of?" -
- المقصود، "بمن عليّ الاعتناء؟" -
he told this story, the story of a man
فحكى هذه القصة، قصة رجلٍ
who had been assaulted, robbed, beaten and abandoned along a dirt road.
تعرّض للاعتداء والسرقة والضرب وأُلقي في طريق موحل.
Upon seeing him, a priest and a Levite, two very influential people of the time,
وعندما رآه كاهنٌ و(ليفيت)، واللذان كانا شخصيتان مؤثرتان في ذلك الوقت،
walked past him without stopping to help.
مرّا أمامه دون التوقف لمساعدته.
After a while, a Samaritan, a very much despised ethnicity at the time, walked by.
وبعد قليل، مرّ سامري، وهو عرق مُحقّر في ذلك الوقت.
Seeing the injured man lying on the ground,
وعند رؤيته لذلك الرجل المصاب ملقىً على الأرض،
he did not ignore him as if he weren't even there.
لم يتجاهله وكأنه غير موجود.
Instead, he felt compassion for this man,
بل شعر بالإشفاق عليه،
which compelled him to act in a very concrete manner.
الأمر الذي دفعه للتصرف بطريقة أخلاقية جداً.
He poured oil and wine on the wounds of the helpless man,
فقد سكب الزيت والنبيذ على جروح الرجل العاجز،
brought him to a hostel
وأخذه إلى نُزلٍ
and paid out of his pocket for him to be assisted.
ودفع له من ماله الخاص ليحصل على المساعدة.
The story of the Good Samaritan is the story of today’s humanity.
إن قصة هذا السامري هي قصة الإنسانية اليوم.
People's paths are riddled with suffering,
فطرقات الناس مليئةٌ بالجروح
as everything is centered around money, and things, instead of people.
لأن كل شيءٍ أصبح يدور حول المال والأشياء بدلاً من الناس.
And often there is this habit, by people who call themselves "respectable,"
وكثيراً ما نلاحظ هذه العادة، من قبل أولئك الذين يسمون أنفسهم "محترمين"،
of not taking care of the others,
وهي عدم الاهتمام لأمر الآخرين،
thus leaving behind thousands of human beings, or entire populations,
وبالتالي يتركون وراءهم آلافاً من البشر، أو شعوباً بأكملها،
on the side of the road.
على جانب الطريق.
Fortunately, there are also those who are creating a new world
لحسن الحظ، هنالك أيضاً من يصنعون عالماً جديداً
by taking care of the other, even out of their own pockets.
من خلال الاهتمام بالآخر، حتى لو على حسابهم الشخصي.
Mother Teresa actually said:
وقد قالت الأمر تيريزا:
"One cannot love, unless it is at their own expense."
"لا يمكن للمرء أن يحب دون أن يبذل أغلى ما لديه"
We have so much to do, and we must do it together.
لدينا الكثير للقيام به، وعلينا فعله معاً.
But how can we do that with all the evil we breathe every day?
ولكن كيف يمكننا القيام بذلك بوجود كل هذا الشر الذي نتنفسه يومياً؟
Thank God,
الحمد لله،
no system can nullify our desire to open up to the good,
لا يمكن لأيّ نظام أن يلغي رغبتنا بالانفتاح إلى الخير،
to compassion and to our capacity to react against evil,
والتعاطف، وقدرتنا على مجابهة الشر،
all of which stem from deep within our hearts.
والتي تنبع جميعها من أعماق قلوبنا.
Now you might tell me,
الآن قد تقول لي،
"Sure, these are beautiful words,
"طبعاً، هذه الكلمات جميلة،
but I am not the Good Samaritan, nor Mother Teresa of Calcutta."
ولكنني لست السامري الصالح أو الأم تيزيزا في كالكوتا."
On the contrary: we are precious, each and every one of us.
وبالمقابل: إننا ثمينون، جميعاً.
Each and every one of us is irreplaceable in the eyes of God.
فكل واحد منا لا يمكن الاستغناء عنه في أعين الله.
Through the darkness of today's conflicts,
وخلال ظلام صراعات اليوم،
each and every one of us can become a bright candle,
يمكن لكل واحد منا أن يصبح شمعةً مضيئة،
a reminder that light will overcome darkness,
وإثباتاً بأن النور سيتغلّب على الظلام،
and never the other way around.
لا العكس أبداً.
To Christians, the future does have a name,
بالنسبة للمسيحيين، فالمستقبل له اسم،
and its name is Hope.
واسمه الأمل.
Feeling hopeful does not mean to be optimistically naïve
أن تكون مفعماً بالأمل لا يعني أن تكون متفائلاً ساذجاً
and ignore the tragedy humanity is facing.
وتتجاهل المأساة التي تواجهها الإنسانية.
Hope is the virtue of a heart
فالأمل هو فضيلة القلب
that doesn't lock itself into darkness, that doesn't dwell on the past,
الذي لا يحبس نفسه في الظلام، ولا يعلق بالماضي،
does not simply get by in the present, but is able to see a tomorrow.
ولا يمكن التعايش معه بسهولة في الحاضر، ولكنه قادر على رؤية الغد.
Hope is the door that opens onto the future.
الأمل هو الباب المفتوح إلى المستقبل.
Hope is a humble, hidden seed of life
وهو بذرة الحياة المتواضعة الخفيّة
that, with time, will develop into a large tree.
التي، مع الوقت، ستتحول إلى شجرةٍ كبيرة.
It is like some invisible yeast that allows the whole dough to grow,
فهو كالخميرة غير المرئية التي تجعل العجينة تكبر،
that brings flavor to all aspects of life.
والتي تضفي نكهةً على جميع جوانب الحياة.
And it can do so much,
كما يمكنه فعل الكثير،
because a tiny flicker of light that feeds on hope
لأن وميضاً صغيراً من النور يتغذّى على الأمل
is enough to shatter the shield of darkness.
كافٍ لتحطيم درعٍ من الظلام.
A single individual is enough for hope to exist,
إن شخصاً واحداً هو كافٍ لإيجاد الأمل،
and that individual can be you.
وهذا الشخص قد يكون أنت.
And then there will be another "you," and another "you,"
ثم سيكون هنالك "أنت" آخر و"أنت" آخر،
and it turns into an "us."
ومن ثم تتحول إلى "نحن".
And so, does hope begin when we have an "us?"
وهكذا، هل يبدأ الأمل عندما يكون لدينا "نحن"؟
No.
لا.
Hope began with one "you."
الأمل يبدأ بـ "أنت" واحد.
When there is an "us," there begins a revolution.
أما عندما يكون هنالك "نحن" فتبدأ الثورة.
The third message I would like to share today
الرسالة الثالثة التي أود مشاركتها معكم اليوم
is, indeed, about revolution: the revolution of tenderness.
هي، في الواقع، عن الثورة: ثورة الرأفة.
And what is tenderness?
وما هي الرأفة؟
It is the love that comes close and becomes real.
إنها ذلك الحبّ الذي يقترب ويصبح حقيقياً.
It is a movement that starts from our heart
إنها حركة تبدأ من قلوبنا
and reaches the eyes, the ears and the hands.
وتصل لأعيننا، آذاننا، وأيدينا.
Tenderness means to use our eyes to see the other,
الرأفة تعني استخدام أعيننا لرؤية الآخر،
our ears to hear the other,
وآذاننا لسماع الآخر،
to listen to the children, the poor, those who are afraid of the future.
لسماع الأطفال والفقراء وأولئك الخائفين من المستقبل.
To listen also to the silent cry of our common home,
للإنصات كذلك للبكاء الصامت لوطننا المشترك،
of our sick and polluted earth.
لأرضنا المريضة والملوثة.
Tenderness means to use our hands and our heart
الرأفة تعني استخدام أيدينا وقلوبنا
to comfort the other,
لإراحة الآخر.
to take care of those in need.
لرعاية المحتاجين.
Tenderness is the language of the young children,
الرأفة هي لغة الأطفال الصغار،
of those who need the other.
لغة أولئك الذين يحتاجون الآخر.
A child’s love for mom and dad
إن حبّ الطفل لأمّه وأبيه
grows through their touch, their gaze, their voice, their tenderness.
ينمو من خلال لمساتهم ونظراتهم وصوتهم ورأفتهم.
I like when I hear parents
أحب أن أسمع الآباء
talk to their babies, adapting to the little child,
يتحدّثون إلى أطفالهم ويتكيّفون مع سنّهم
sharing the same level of communication.
ويشاركونهم نفس درجة التواصل.
This is tenderness: being on the same level as the other.
هذه هي الرأفة: أن تكون بنفس درجة الآخر.
God himself descended into Jesus to be on our level.
الله بنفسه نزل إلى يسوع ليكون بمستواه.
This is the same path the Good Samaritan took.
إنّه نفس الطريق الذي اتّخذه السامري الصالح.
This is the path that Jesus himself took.
وهو ذات الطريق الذي اتّخذه المسيح بنفسه.
He lowered himself,
فقد خفض نفسه،
he lived his entire human existence
وعاش حياته البشرية بأكملها
practicing the real, concrete language of love.
ممارساً لغة الحب الحقيقية الملموسة.
Yes, tenderness is the path of choice
نعم، الرأفة هي الطريق المفضل
for the strongest, most courageous men and women.
للرجال والنساء الأكثر قوة وشجاعة.
Tenderness is not weakness; it is fortitude.
الرأفة ليست ضعفاً، بل شجاعة.
It is the path of solidarity, the path of humility.
إنها طريق التضامن، طريق التواضع.
Please, allow me to say it loud and clear:
رجاءً، اسمحوا لي أن أقولها بصوتٍ عالٍ وواضح:
the more powerful you are,
كلما كنت أقوى،
the more your actions will have an impact on people,
كلما تركت أفعالكَ أثراً لدى الناس،
the more responsible you are to act humbly.
كلما أصبحت مسؤولاً للتصرف بتواضع أكثر.
If you don’t, your power will ruin you, and you will ruin the other.
إن لم تفعل ذلك، ستدمّرك قوتك، وبالتالي ستدّمرُ أنت الآخرين بدورك.
There is a saying in Argentina:
هنالك حكمة في الأرجنتين تقول:
"Power is like drinking gin on an empty stomach."
القوة كشرب النبيذ على معدةٍ فارغة.
You feel dizzy, you get drunk, you lose your balance,
ستشعر بالدوار، وتسكر، وتفقد توازنك،
and you will end up hurting yourself and those around you,
وسينتهي بك المطاف وأنت تؤذي نفسك ومن حولك
if you don’t connect your power with humility and tenderness.
إذا لم يرافق قوّتك التواضع والرأفة.
Through humility and concrete love, on the other hand,
من خلال التواضع والحب القويّ، بشكلٍ آخر،
power – the highest, the strongest one – becomes a service, a force for good.
تصبح السلطة، العليا والأقوى، خدمةً ودافعاً للخير.
The future of humankind isn't exclusively in the hands of politicians,
إن مستقبل الجنس البشريّ ليس محصوراً بأيدي السياسيين
of great leaders, of big companies.
والقادة العظماء والشركات الكبرى،
Yes, they do hold an enormous responsibility.
نعم، هم يتحمّلون مسؤولية ضخمة،
But the future is, most of all, in the hands of those people
لكن المستقبل، في معظمه، بأيدي أولئك
who recognize the other as a "you"
الذين يعرفون الآخر كـ "أنت"،
and themselves as part of an "us."
وأنفسهم كجزء من "نحن".
We all need each other.
جميعنا نحتاج بعضنا البعض.
And so, please, think of me as well with tenderness,
لذا، رجاءً، انظروا لي أيضاً بعين الرأفة،
so that I can fulfill the task I have been given
حتى أستطيع تحقيق المهمة التي أوكلت لي
for the good of the other,
من أجل مصلحة الآخر،
of each and every one, of all of you,
من أجل الكل، من أجلكم جميعاً،
of all of us.
من أجلنا كلّنا.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.